This video explains how to use the Arclight to perform the fundal red reflex by selecting the brightest light setting.
Make sure the lens rack is at the top, where there is no lens power in the sight hole.
At arm's length, observe the reflex in both eyes at the same time.
Compare the brightness and colour between the two eyes.
In a normal examination, there should be no overall difference in the brightness and colour between the two eyes.
In white and Asian babies, the reflex can look more orange and yellow.
These appearances are still all normal as the overall colour and brightness are the same between the two eyes.
An abnormal reflex is when there is a persistent, real difference in the brightness and colour between the two eyes.
This may be a displaced corneal reflection, a dark patch present within the reflex of one eye or both eyes, or a completely absent red reflex.
An abnormal reflex test can indicate the presence of cataract, retinoblastoma, corneal scar, squint, or refractive error.
These all require further assessment by a specialist.